A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, The Fund for Adult Education (FAE) records FA716
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Administrative records, 1950-1972; I
  - FAE Office Files, 1950-1969; 3
    - Statement of Purpose, 1951-1953 (Box 16, Folder 179)
    - Surveys by Cresap, McCormick and Paget (Box 17)
      - Great Books Foundation, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 180)
      - Management of Adult Liberal Educ. Programs, 1957 (Box 17, Folder 181)
      - Three National Organizations, 1957; 1958 (?) (Box 17, Folder 182)
    - Report of Activities, 1951-1956 (Box 17, Folder 183)
    - Toward the Liberally Educated Executive, 1957-1960 (Box 17, Folder 184)
    - Ways of Mankind (Copyright, Agreements, script), 1952-1967 (Box 17, Folder 185)
      Copyright, Agreements, script
    - White Plains Facility, 1954; 1960-1963 (Box 17, Folder 186)
    - White Plains Facility, 1963-1964 (Box 17, Folder 187)
  - Photographs, 4
    Subseries 4, (Box 17) contains photographs of FAE staff and trustees, and of trustees of the Ford Foundation.
    - Board Members and Officers of FAE, and Foundation Trustees, 1950s; 1960 (Box 17, Folder 188-190)
      May include Officers of TFAE.
  - Office Files of G.H. Griffiths, 1955-1972; 5
    Subseries 5, G.H. Griffiths' files (Boxes 18-19) includes reports, correspondence, notes, and a speech transcript. To a limited extent they reflect the shift in educational concerns to the Ford Foundation after the dissolution of FAE. Although materials include Griffiths' tenure at FAE, they primarily cover his responsibilities as Associate Director of the Ford Foundation's Education Program, 1961-1967. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject, notably including materials produced by the Ford Foundation grantee, St. Louis University, and the University Council on Education for Public Responsibility (1965-1968), which was initiated by the FAE but taken over by the Ford Foundation.
    - Adult Basic Education, 1961-1964; 1966 (Box 18, Folder 191)
    - Adult Basic Education, "The Ford Foundation and Adult Education", 1964 (Box 18, Folder 192)
    - Board Docket Items, 1958 (Box 18, Folder 193)
    - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1962-1966 (Box 18, Folder 194)
    - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1966-1967 (Box 18, Folder 195)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1965; 1972 (Box 18, Folder 196)
    - Correspondence routed to Griffiths, 1960-1962 (Box 18, Folder 197)
    - Educational Television, 1964-1966 (Box 18, Folder 198)
    - Financial Statements, 1960-1962 (Box 18, Folder 199)
    - Five Year Grant Proposal, 1955 (?) (Box 18, Folder 200)
    - National Association for Public School Adult Education (NAPSAE), 1964-1965 (Box 18, Folder 201)
    - "Research in the Fund Program" Speech Transcript, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 202)
    - St. Louis University, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 203)
    - St. Louis University, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 204)
    - St. Louis University, 1964 (Box 19, Folder 205)
    - University Council on Education for Public Responsibility, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 206)
    - University Council on Education for Public Responsibility, 1966-1968 (Box 19, Folder 207)
    - University Council on Education for Public Responsibility: Papers, 1966-1968 (Box 19, Folder 208)
    - University Council on Education for Public Responsibility: Papers, 1966-1968 (Box 19, Folder 209)
- Financial, Legal and Tax Files, 1951-1963; II
  Series 2, Financial, Legal, and Tax Records (1.0 cu. ft.), contain office files, grants- accounting files, program and project costs, and general journals. Materials in the general journals and financial files (Boxes 20-21) include tax, payroll, deeds, grant-payment records, and grant-accounting files, as well as financial statements with signed audits by Price Waterhouse and Co., and correspondence regarding legal and tax concerns. Monthly financial statements, which are summarized yearly in the Price Waterhouse audits, routine bank transfers, and carbon copies of both New York State form 1099 and Federal W2-forms were discarded. All signed correspondence was retained.
  - County Trust Co.: Agreement and Correspondence, 1956-1960; 1962 (Box 20, Folder 210)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted from scholarly access.
  - Cravath, Swaine, and Moore: Correspondence, 1956-1962 (Box 20, Folder 211)
  - Federal Tax: Correspondence, 1961 (Box 20, Folder 212)
  - Federal Tax: Employee Quarterly Income Tax Return, 1956-1960 (Box 20, Folder 213)
  - Federal Tax: Exemption Status of Grantees, Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 20, Folder 214)
  - Federal Tax: Form 990 materials, 1956-1959 (Box 20, Folder 215)
  - Financial Statements (Price Waterhouse & Co. Auditors), 1951-1956 (Box 20, Folder 216)
  - Financial Statements (Price Waterhouse & Co. Auditors), 1957-1963 (Box 20, Folder 217)
  - Income Tax Exemption, 1952-1959 (Box 20, Folder 218)
  - Investments, 1961 (Box 20, Folder 219)
  - New York State: Social Welfare Law, 1957 (Box 20, Folder 220)
  - New York State: Workmen's Compensation, 1960 (Box 20, Folder 221)
  - New York State Tax: Certificate of Non-Residence, 1955-1957 (Box 20, Folder 222)
  - Personnel: Employment records, 1951-1956 (Box 20, Folder 223)
  - Personnel: 'Fletcher, Scott: Approved Expense Accounts, 1956-1961 (Box 21, Folder 224)
  - Personnel: Salaries and Severance Arrangements, 1956-1961 (Box 21, Folder 225)
  - Personnel: Salaries and Severance Arrangements, 1956-1961 (Box 21, Folder 226)
  - Price Waterhouse and Company: Correspondence, 1952; 1955-1963 (Box 21, Folder 227)
  - TIAA-CREF: Annuity Billings, 1951-1953 (Box 21, Folder 228)
  - TIAA-CREF: Annuity Billings, 1959-1962 (Box 21, Folder 229)
  - TIAA-CREF: Annuity Refund, 1959 (Box 21, Folder 230)
  - TIAA-CREF: Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 21, Folder 231)
  - White Plains Facility: Deed, Agreement and Correspondence, 1956-1957; 1960; 1963 (Box 21, Folder 232)
- Grant and Project Files, 1952-1961; III; 47 microform reels
  Series 3, Grant and Project Files, consists primarily of records of institutional grants and projects run internally by FAE, such as the Experimental Discussion Program. The series also contains individual awards files as well as grants-accounting files, which contain records of grant payments and completed request-and-authorization-of-program-action forms.
  Several files, particularly program costs files and several television station financial files, are not contained in the collection.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Series 3 is open for research. The material has been reformatted to microfilm. Scholarly access is provided to the microfilm only.
  The original paper records are not in the RAC collection.
  - Adult Education Association of the United States (Reel 4724)
  - Advertising Council, Inc.: Attachments only (Reel 4724)
  - Aid to Projects of Local Libraries: Attachments only (Reel 4724)
  - Akron, University of (Reel 4724)
  - American Alumni Council (Reel 4724)
  - American Assembly (Reel 4725)
  - American Council on Education (Reel 4725)
    Related Materials
    see also: Penn State Meeting on Educational Television
  - American Ethical Union, Inc. (Reel 4725)
  - American Foundation for Continuing Education (Reel 4725)
  - American Heritage Council (Reel 4725)
  - American Heritage Council (Reel 4726)
  - American Humanics Foundation: Attachments only (Reel 4726)
  - American Institute for Public Opinion: Attachments only (Reel 4726)
  - American Labor Education Service (Reel 4726)
  - American Labor Education Service (Reel 4727)
  - American Law Institute (Reel 4727)
  - American Library Association (Reel 4727)
  - American Library Association (Reel 4728)
  - American Management Association (Reel 4728)
  - American University (Reel 4728)
  - AMVETS (Reel 4728)
  - Antioch College (Reel 4728)
  - Antioch College (Reel 4729)
  - Bethany College (Reel 4729)
  - Birmingham Southern College (Reel 4729)
  - Boston University (Reel 4729)
  - British Columbia, University of (Reel 4729)
  - British Columbia, University of (Reel 4730)
  - Brookings Institute (Reel 4730)
  - California, University of (Reel 4730)
  - Canadian Association for Adult Education (Reel 4730)
  - Canadian Association for Adult Education (Reel 4731)
  - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (Reel 4731)
  - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (Reel 4732)
  - Chatauqua Institution (Reel 4732)
  - Chicago, University of (Reel 4732)
  - Chicago, University of (Reel 4733)
  - Chicago, University of (Reel 4734)
  - Cleveland Council on World Affairs (Reel 4734)
  - (The) Cleveland Story (Reel 4734)
  - Colbert, Roy J. (Reel 4734)
  - Columbia University (Reel 4734)
  - Committee for Economic Development (Reel 4735)
  - Council of National Organizations (Reel 4735)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (Reel 4735)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (Reel 4736)
  - Denver Adult Education Program (Reel 4736)
  - Detroit, University of (Reel 4736)
  - Educational Television and Radio Center (Reel 4736)
  - Emory University (Reel 4736)
  - Encyclopaedia Brittanica Films, Inc. (Reel 4736)
  - Farm Foundation (Reel 4736)
  - Fight Blight, Inc. (Reel 4736)
  - Film Council of America (Reel 4736)
  - Fisk University (Reel 4737)
  - Fiske, Marjorie (Reel 4737)
  - Foreign Policy Association (Reel 4737)
    see: World Affairs Council of Los Angeles
  - FAE: Internal Projects
    - FAE: Internal Projects: Experimental Discussion Program (Project #118) (Reel 4738)
      Projects Include: Humanities for Adult Education (Stephens College); Life Under Communism; Ways of Mankind; World Affairs are Your Affairs; You and Your Community; and Your Money or Your Life.
    - FAE: Internal Projects: Experimental Discussion Program (Project #118) (Reel 4739)
    - FAE: Internal Projects: Experimental Discussion Program (Project #118) (Reel 4740)
    - FAE: Internal Projects: Experimental Discussion Program (Project #118) (Reel 4741)
    - FAE: Internal Projects: Experimental Discussion Program (Project #118) (Reel 4746)
    - FAE: Internal Projects: Experimental Discussion Program (Project #118) (Reel 4747)
    - FAE: Internal Projects: Experimental Discussion Program (Project #118) (Reel 4749)
    - FAE: Internal Projects: Experimental Discussion Program (Project #118) (Reel 4751)
    - Experimental Discussion Program: Commercial Publications (1202) (Reel 4745)
    - FAE: Internal Projects - Leadership Training Awards, 1952-1961 (Reel 4740)
    - FAE: Other Internal Projects (Reel 4740)
      - Lectureships (388): Bryson, Lyman; Flemming, Arthur; Perkins,Dexter; Randall, Clarence; Redfield, Robert. (Reel 4747)
      - Occasional Papers (498) (Reel 4747)
      - Occasional Papers (498) (Reel 4748)
      - Television: Engineering and Legal Expense Project (574) (Reel 4748)
      - Senior Citizens Project (596) (Reel 4748)
      - Rural Adult Education - Investigation: Australia (635) (Reel 4748)
      - Alumni Education Investigation (696) (Reel 4748)
      - Test Centers: General Files (754) (Reel 4748)
        - Test Centers: Project files
          - Akron, University of (Reel 4748)
          - Arkansas, University of (Reel 4748)
          - UCLA (Reel 4748)
          - Denver, University of (Reel 4748)
          - Kansas City, University of (Reel 4748)
          - Kansas City, University of (Reel 4742)
          - Louisville, University of (Reel 4742)
          - Macalester College (Reel 4742)
          - Pasadena Area programs (Reel 4742)
          - Virginia, University of (Reel 4742)
          - Utah, University of (Reel 4742)
          - Whittier College (Reel 4742)
      - Test Centers: Attachment Files: General (Reel 4743)
    - Special Reports on Various Categories of the Fund Program (812) (Reel 4743)
    - Synthesis of Surveys and Publications of Survey Summaries (813) (Reel 4743)
    - Program Exploration (878) (Reel 4743)
    - Evaluation (879) (Reel 4743)
    - Conferences, Institutes and Publications (983) (Reel 4743)
    - Travel and Conference Expenses of Visitors to Fund Projects (1109) (Reel 4743)
    - Education in Public Responsibility (1184) (Reel 4743)
    - Education in Public Responsibility (1184) (Reel 4744)
    - Education in Public Responsibility (1184): Arden House Conference (Reel 4744)
    - Education in Public Responsibility (1184): Arden House Conference (Reel 4745)
    - Professional Advice for Achievement of Self Support (Great Books Foundation) (1185) (Reel 4745)
    - Fact Finding Research and Evaluation (1214) (Reel 4745)
    - Fact Finding Research and Evaluation (1214) (Reel 4750)
    - Promotion (1254) (Reel 4750)
    - Conference on Study-Discussion at Salt Lake City (1406), 1960 (Reel 4750)
    - Study: Professional Advice to Great Books Foundation (1462) (Reel 4750)
  - Georgia, University of (Reel 4750)
  - Goddard College (Reel 4750)
  - Goldberg, Maxwell H. (Reel 4750)
  - Goucher College (Reel 4750)
  - Great Books Foundation (Reel 4750)
  - Greater Cincinnati T.V. Educational Foundation (Reel 4750)
  - Harvard University (Reel 4750)
  - Helms Memorial Award (Reel 4737)
  - (Martha Crampton), Howard, Memorial Fund (Reel 4737)
  - Hudson, Robert B. (Reel 4737)
  - Indiana University (Reel 4737)
  - International Ladies Garment Workers Union (Reel 4752)
  - Inter-University Labor Education Committee (Reel 4737)
  - Inter-University Labor Education Committee (Reel 4752)
  - Iowa Farm Bureau Federation (Reel 4752)
  - Joint Committee on Educational Television (Reel 4752)
  - Joint Council on Economic Education (Reel 4752)
  - Land Grant Colleges and Universities, Association of (Reel 4752)
  - Long Beach (Calif.) Public Library (Reel 4752)
  - Lowell Institute Cooperative Broadcasting Council (Reel 4752)
  - Loyola University (Chicago) (Reel 4752)
  - Matthews, Joseph L./(B.L.) Mazel, Inc. (Reel 4753)
  - Michigan State University (Reel 4753)
  - Mid-Atlantic Regional Conference: Attachments Only (Reel 4753)
  - Middle States Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools (Reel 4753)
  - Minneapolis Symphony Orchestra (Reel 4753)
  - Minnesota, University of (Reel 4753)
  - Moorhead, Hugh S. (Reel 4753)
  - Moss, Tobias (Reel 4753)
  - National Association of Educational Broadcasters (Reel 4753)
  - National Association of Educational Broadcasters (Reel 4754)
  - National Association of Public School Adult Educators (Reel 4754)
  - National Broadcasting Company, Inc. (Reel 4754)
  - National Citizens' Committee for Educ. Television (Reel 4754)
  - National Education Association (Reel 4754)
  - National Education Association (Reel 4755)
  - National Educational Television and Radio Center (Reel 4755)
  - National 4 H Club Foundation (Reel 4755)
    see also: Study-Discussion: Youth Organizations
  - National Institute of Labor Education (Reel 4755)
  - National Institute of Labor Education (Reel 4756)
  - National Management Association (Reel 4756)
  - National Social Welfare Assembly (Reel 4756)
  - National University Extension Association (Reel 4756)
  - New York State Department of Education (Reel 4756)
  - New York University (Reel 4756)
  - North Carolina, University of (Reel 4756)
  - North Dakota State Teachers College (Reel 4756)
  - Oglethorpe University (Reel 4756)
  - Ohio State University (Reel 4756)
  - Oklahoma, University of (Reel 4756)
  - Oklahoma, University of (Reel 4757)
    Including files of the University Council on Education for Public Responsibility
  - Oregon State System of Higher Education (Reel 4757)
  - Pacifica Foundation (Reel 4757)
  - Pasadena Area Liberal Arts Center (Reel 4757)
  - Peckham, Morse (Reel 4757)
  - Penn State Meeting on Educational Television (Reel 4757)
    See also: American Council on Education.
  - Pennsylvania State University (Reel 4757)
  - Pennsylvania State University (Reel 4758)
  - Pennsylvania, University of: The People Act (Reel 4758)
  - Pomona College (Reel 4758)
  - Promotion Consultants, Inc. (Reel 4758)
  - Pulling, R.J. (Reel 4758)
  - Recording for the Blind (Reel 4758)
  - Recording for the Blind (Reel 4759)
  - Retirement Council, Inc. (Reel 4759)
  - Sheats, Paul H. (Reel 4759)
  - Smith, Hilda (Reel 4759)
  - Southern Regional Education Board (Reel 4759)
  - Southwestern at Memphis (Reel 4759)
  - Southwestern at Memphis (Reel 4760)
  - State Cooperative Extension Service (Cooperative Extension Service (CES)) (Reel 4760)
    Includes general and institutional files.
    - Arizona, University of (Reel 4760)
    - Illinois, University of (Reel 4760)
    - Michigan State University (Reel 4760)
    - Montana State College (Reel 4760)
    - Pennsylvannia State University (Reel 4760)
    - Texas A & M (Reel 4760)
  - Stensland, Per G. (Reel 4760)
  - Stephens College (Reel 4760)
  - Study-Discussion: Youth Organizations (Reel 4760)
  - Survey of National Voluntary Organizations: Reports by Helen Hamilton Woods (Reel 4761)
  - Syracuse University (Reel 4761)
  - Television: General (Reel 4761)
  - Television Stations (Reel 4761)
    - Albuquerque, NM.: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - Ames, IA (Reel 4761)
    - Ames, IA (Reel 4761)
    - Atlanta, GA.: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - Austin and San Antonio, TX: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - East Lansing, MI: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - Gainsville, FL: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - Lafayette, IN: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - New Orleans, LA: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - New York, NY: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - Pittsburgh, PA: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - Sacramento and Stockton, CA: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - St. Louis, MO: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - University, AL: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
    - Urbana, IL: Attachments only (Reel 4761)
  - Tennessee, University of (Reel 4761)
  - Toward the Liberally Educated Executive (Reel 4761)
  - Tufts University (Reel 4761)
  - Tulane University (Reel 4762)
  - United States Department of Agriculture (Reel 4762)
  - University Council on Education for Public Responsibility (Reel 4762)
    See also: Oklahoma, University of.
  - Utah, University (Reel 4762)
  - Vassar Summer Institute (Reel 4762)
  - Virginia, University of (Reel 4762)
  - Wabash Valley (Ind.) Education Center (Reel 4762)
  - Walt Foundation (Reel 4762)
  - Washington University (Reel 4762)
  - Washington, University of (Reel 4762)
  - Wayne State University (Reel 4762)
  - West Georgia College (Reel 4762)
  - Westchester Community College, Inc. (Reel 4762)
  - Westchester Community College, Inc. (Reel 4763)
  - Westchester County Federation for Women's Club (Reel 4763)
  - Western Reserve University (Reel 4763)
  - Wishengrad, Morton (Reel 4763)
  - Woods, Helen Hamilton (Reel 4763)
    See: Survey of National Voluntary Organizations
  - World Affairs Council of Los Angeles (Reel 4763)
  - Young Men's Christian Association (Reel 4763)
    See: Study-Discussion: Youth Organizations.
  - Young Women's Christian Association (Reel 4763)
  - Television Stations Assistance: Financial Files (Reel 4764)
    Records for purchase of TV equipment by public education TV stations in the noted cities. Cities from Milwaukee, WI to Urbana, IL are not documented in this file.
    - Albuquerque, NM (Reel 4764)
    - Ames, IA (Reel 4764)
    - Austin, TX (Reel 4764)
    - Atlanta, GA (Reel 4764)
    - Bloomington, IN (Reel 4764)
    - Boston, MA (Reel 4764)
    - Chapel Hill, NC (Reel 4764)
    - Chicago, IL (Reel 4764)
    - Cincinnati, OH (Reel 4764)
    - Columbus, OH (Reel 4764)
    - Dallas, TX (Reel 4764)
    - Denver, CO (Reel 4764)
    - Detroit, MI (Reel 4764)
    - Durham, NH (Reel 4764)
    - East Lansing, MI (Reel 4764)
    - Gainesville, FL (Reel 4764)
    - Houston, TX (Reel 4764)
    - Jacksonville, FL (Reel 4764)
    - Lincoln, NE (Reel 4764)
    - Los Angeles, CA (Reel 4764)
    - Madison, WI (Reel 4764)
    - Memphis, TN (Reel 4764)
    - Miami, FL (Reel 4764)
  - Financial/Grants Accounting Files
    - Adult Education Association/USA - American Ethical Union (Reel 4770)
    - American Foundation for Continuing Education - Canadian Association for Adult Education (Reel 4767)
    - Canadian Association for Adult Education: Emory (mid.) (Reel 4765)
    - Emory (mid.): Pennsylvannia State (Reel 4766)
    - University of Pennsylvannia - End (Reel 4768)
  - Individual Awards
    - Adminstrative files (Reel 4745)
    - Leadership Training Awards, A-Carle, 1955-1960 (Reel 4768)
    - Leadership Training Awards, Clayton-End, 1955-1960 (Reel 4770)
      See: FAE Internal Projects: Leadership Training Awards
    - Internships-Scholarships-Fellowships, 1952-1953 (Reel 4745)
    - Internships-Scholarships-Fellowships, 1952-1953 (Reel 4769)
    - Study Grants, 1953-1954 (Reel 4769)